Okay, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is ס"ט, Samech Tet,
sixty-nine, and we pick up four lines from the top, איתיביה אביי,
Etvei Abaye, we have just started בן סורר ומורה, Ben Sorer U'Moreh,
and we have positioned a debate because we had a teaching of
רב חסדא Rav Chisda that if a minor fathers a child, that
child cannot be a בן סורר ומורה Ben Sorer U'Moreh because it
says לאיש בן, Le'ish Ben, and a man has a son, not
a child has a son, and which the גמרא Gemara says obviously
means that he thinks that an under age child, somebody under the
age of thirteen can father a child, and that was said to
be in conflict or it's a debate between him and רבא Rava
because רבא Rava teaches based in the case of a גזל הגר,
Gezel HaGer, stealing from a גר ger and swearing falsely, and then
the גר ger dies, that you don't have to worry if the
גר ger has heirs if the גר ger was a minor because
a minor cannot father a child. So we have a debate between
רבא Rava and רב חסדא Rav Chisda whether a minor can father
a child. So let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes with this.
Four lines from the top, ס"ט עמוד א'. Samech Tet Amud Aleph.
איתיביה אביי, Etvei Abaye, אביי Abaye asks this. איש, Ish, it says
איש. Ish. אין לי אלא איש, Ein li ela Ish, I only
know that we're talking about somebody who is a man. The context
here is a case of a שפחה חרופה, Shifcha Charufa, a slave
woman who's sort of partly married to a slave and a man
sleeps with her and there's a special קרבן Korban for that case.
So it says, and רש"י Rashi pulls the פסוק, pasuk, ואיש כי
ישכב את אשה שכבת זרע. Ve'ish Ki Yishkav Et Isha Shichvat Zera.
And literally that's actually one of the places where the Torah explicitly
describes it as שכבת זרע, Shichvat Zera, you know, a sleeping of
a seminal emission, and it's one of the places where הלכה Halacha
actually requires that there be גמר ביאה, Gemar Biah, not just הערה,
Ha'arah, where it be a full penetration. Anyway, so אביי Abaye says
איש, Ish, אין לי אלא איש, Ein li ela Ish, I only
know that that case applies if it is a man. בן ט'
שנים ויום אחד שראוי לביאה מנין, Ben Tet Shanim V'Yom Echad She'rauy
Lebiah Minayin,
how do I know to even include a case of somebody that
is nine years old and one day, which as we know is
defined as an act of intercourse? תלמוד לומר, Talmud Lomar, ואיש, Ve'ish,
the extra ו'. vav. אין לי אלא, Ein li ela, so אמר
ליה, amar lei, יש לו ואינו מוליד. Yesh lo v'eino molid. So
the גמרא, Gemara, so anyway, the point is that that is a
פסוק pasuk which says שכבת זרע, Shichvat Zera, and the requirement for
שפחה חרופה Shifcha Charufa is ראוי להוליד, Rauy L'Holid, excuse me, ראוי
להזריע, Rauy L'Hazriya, that you need גמר ביאה, Gemar Biah, you need
a full penetration because it is a context in which it's fit
to be to seminal emission, to ejaculation. So the גמרא Gemara concedes
that yes, under thirteen has seminal emission, but יש
לו ואינו מוליד, Yesh lo v'eino molid, but it is not able
to procreate. Okay, so there is seminal emission, but the semen is
not potent yet, that is the claim. כצבועה שלא הביאה שליש, Kitzvua
Shelo Heivia Shlish, like grain that has not yet become a third
ripe, and in that case, you know, there is grain there but
it has not yet the ability if you were to plant the
seed, it would not bring about more grain. Okay, so it's not
yet fertile. Okay, דהויית, davi'it, like
that is what it can be compared to. דבי חזקיה תנא, Debei
Chizkiyah Tana, the house of חזקיה Chizkiyah taught, וכי יזיד איש, Vechi
Yazid Ish, if a man, you know, lies in wait, we just
had this in פרשת משפטים, Parshat Mishpatim, על רעהו להרגו בערמה, Al
Re'ehu Lehorgo Be'arma, you know, against his friend, he willfully lies in
wait against his friend to kill him with deception, you know, or
so then מעם מזבחי תקחנו למות. Me'im Mizbechi Tikachenu Lamut. But we're
making a דרש drash on the word כי יזיד, Ki Yazid,
and we'll see that that's based like on the word ויזד יעקב
נזיד, Vayazed Yaakov Nazid, like cook. So let's take a look. וכי
יזיד איש, Vechi Yazid Ish, איש מזיד ומזריע, Ish Mazid U'Mazria, a
man, the semen sort of inside of him, you know, ripens, cooks,
and then he can be fertile. ואין קטן מזיד ומזריע. Ve'ein Katan
Mazid U'Mazria. So it has nothing to do with the פסוק pasuk
which is talking about somebody who kills במזיד, be'mazid, but from that
word of כי יזיד, Ki Yazid, we're learning out that only when
you're a man can you be fertile. אמר ליה רב מרדכי לרב
אשי, Amar lei Rav Mordechai leRav Ashi, מאי משמע דהאי מזיד לישנא
דבישולי הוא, Mai mashma dehai mazid lishna debishulei hu, where are you
getting this דרשה drasha that the word מזיד mazid is sense of,
you know, cooking and ripening? דכתיב, Dichviv, ויזד יעקב נזיד. Vayazed Yaakov
Nazid. Okay, so that is consistent with the teaching of רבא Rava
that only when somebody is an adult, a man, only after the
age of בר מצוה, bar mitzvah, is he, is his semen fertile.
Of course, biologically, it is not dependent on that. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this, ותנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, V'tana d'bei Rabbi
Yishmael, בן ולא אב, Ben V'lo Av, so one minute, but we
have a teaching in the house of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael that
says, you know,
that excludes the case of if the בן סורר ומורה Ben Sorer
U'Moreh himself has fathered a child. Okay, so until now we were
excluding the case of a בן סורר ומורה Ben Sorer U'Moreh who
had been fathered by a child. Here we are excluding the case
of when the בן סורר ומורה Ben Sorer U'Moreh himself has fathered
a child. Only if he is a son, not if he's already
a father. Okay, and so here again, even though now we know
that a בן סורר ומורה Ben Sorer U'Moreh is bar mitzvahed, okay,
but still, is there enough time for him to father a child?
If you say that his semen is only potent starting at the
age of בר מצוה. bar mitzvah. So let's... So let’s take a
look. Okay, בן ben ולא אב *ben v'lo av*.
היכי דמי *heichei dami*, what’s the case? אילימא דעיבר בתר דאייתי שתי
שערות *ileima d'ibar basar d'aisei shtei searos*, if the woman he impregnated,
you know, had happened after he brought two pubic hair hairs,
so meaning, you know, the conception happened once he was already an
adult, בר מצוה *bar mitzvah*, which is what we’re claiming that it
has to be at that stage where the semen is potent. ואוליד
מקמי דליקוף זקן *v'olid mikamei d'leikef zakan*, but now in order for
him to be a father, this woman has to give birth before
his lower beard fills out, okay? So מי קא שכיח כולי האי
*mi ka shechiach kulei hai*? But there’s there’s not enough time, you
know, the range of time, the amount of time that a window
that a somebody could become a בן סורר ומורה ben sorer umoreh,
*ben sorer umoreh* is very short. Why?
How do you know how long it’s going to take for the
pubic hair to fill out? Well, דאמר רב חסדא *d'amar Rav Chisda*,
Rav Chisda says, interesting Chisda is Aramaic for ציצית *tzitzit*, just a
little interesting fun fact there, but doesn’t Rav Chisda teach כל ימיו
של בן סורר ומורה ben sorer umoreh אינו אלא ela, ג' חדשים
*kol yamav shel ben sorer umoreh eino ela gimel chodashim*, that a
בן סורר ומורה ben sorer umoreh *ben sorer umoreh* from the time
he’s בר מצוה *bar mitzvah* it’s only three months? Now how that
fits with our משנה mishna. *mishnah* that says when the pubic hair
fills out, we’ll worry about it in a minute. But for now
let’s take the assumption that that הלכה *halacha* is true, that it
can’t be more than three months. So if you say that when
somebody is only able, that a man’s semen, a boy’s semen is
only potent once he becomes בר מצוה *bar mitzvah*, there’s no way
we can exclude a בן סורר ומורה ben sorer umoreh *ben sorer
umoreh* who’s a father because he would have had to father a
child he would have had to have intercourse after he was בר
מצוה *bar mitzvah*, and then he wouldn’t, you know, he would not
be able to be a father within the three month window. אלא
לאו *ela lav*, so the only case could be דעיבר מקמי דלייתי
שתי שערות ואוליד מקמי דליקוף זקן *d'ibar mikamei d'laisi shtei searos v'olid
mikamei d'leikef zakan*. So the only way that it could be a
case that he could be a father and possibly be a בן
סורר ומורה ben sorer umoreh, *ben sorer umoreh* is if he had
intercourse before he was בר מצוה *bar mitzvah* and then the woman
gave birth while he was still in the three month window. ושמע
מינה קטן מוליד *u'shma mina katan molid*, that shows that the semen
of a minor can be potent, ושמע מינה קטן מוליד *u'shma mina
katan molid*, that a minor can actually father a child. לא lo.
*lo*, no, ולעולם דעיבר בתר דאייתי שתי שערות *u'leolam d'ibar basar d'aisei
shtei searos*, the woman became pregnant after he brought two hairs, ואוליד
בתר דאקוף זקן *v'olid basar d'akef zakan*, and he gave birth after
his pubic hair filled out and after the three she gave birth
excuse me and after the three months. Okay, if that’s so, then
how he’s already can’t be a בן סורר ומורה Ben Sorer Umoreh
*ben sorer umoreh* because it’s more than three months. So why do
you need to exclude him from this דרשה *drasha* of, you know,
בן ben ולא אב *ben v'lo av*? ודקא קשיא דרב חסדא *v'deka
kashya d'Rav Chisda*, you’re bothered about Rav Chisda’s teaching that the whole
window is three months,
so here anyway we’re saying that the birth was after anyway his
pubic hair filled out. כי אתא רב דימי אמר *ki ata Rav
Dimi amar*, when Rav Dimi came he explained what this teaching was
to exclude בן ולא אב *ben v’lo av*. אמרי במערבא *amri b'ma'arava*,
what they say in מערבא *Ma'arava* is בן ולא הראוי לקרותו אב
*ben v'lo hara'ui likroso av*. We’re not saying that once once he’s
a father he can’t be a בן סורר ומורה ben sorer u'moreh
*ben sorer umoreh*, once he is a potential father he can’t be
a בן סורר ומורה ben sorer u'moreh, *ben sorer umoreh*. And that’s
actually why the why Rav Chisda says there’s a three month window.
Because we now we understand where that idea is coming from, because
when at what stage would an adult boy be able to be
called a father? Well, thirteen years and three months. Why? Because he
would have he could have intercourse on the day of his בר
מצוה *bar mitzvah*, all right, and assuming that that is only when
the semen becomes potent, and then it takes three months for the
woman to show that she’s pregnant, הלכתית *halachically* you know there’s a
after three months you know the woman is seen to be showing
that she’s pregnant, that has a lot of הלכה *halacha* implications that
you can see it and it’s visible at that time. And at
that stage you say oh he’s the father of that baby that’s
going to be born. Okay, so that’s where Rav Chisda gets his
three month limit, that it’s that so it’s not a problem at
all. You’re right he will give birth after the three month limit,
but the exclusion is not that he’s already a father but that
it limits the window till the time until a time when in
theory he could be a father, and that’s three months after his
בר מצוה *bar mitzvah*, theoretically be called a father, not yet actually
be a father. Okay, and that’s exactly the teaching of Rav Chisda.
גופא *gufa*, so very nice. So now we have solved that problem
and we have explained where Rav Chisda gets his teaching from gets
his הלכה *halacha* from. Now let’s go back to that teaching. גופא
*gufa*, אמר רב חסדא אמר רב שבתאי amar rav shaptai, כל ימיו
של בן סורר ומורה ben sorer u'moreh אינו אלא ג' חדשים בלבד
*amar Rav Chisda amar Rav Shabtai kol yamav shel ben sorer umoreh
eino ela gimel chodashim bilvad*. Three months. And now we’ve explained why.
והאנן תנן *v'hanan tnan*, but our משנה *mishnah* teaches only when the
beard fills up? המשיקוף *hamasheyakef*? But our משנה *mishnah* teaches only when
the beard fills out. So the Gemara says whichever one comes first.
ג' חדשים אף על גב דלא הקיף *gimel chodashim af al gav
d'lo hekif*, but doesn’t our משנה *mishnah* teach והאנן תנן משיביא שתי
שערות ועד שיקיף *v'hanan tnan misheyavi shtei searos v'ad sheyakef*. יקיף זקן
until the full beard fills out, so that's not three months, that
could be longer. So the גמרא Gemara says whichever one comes first.
הקיף זקן אף על גב דלא מלו, hikif zakan af al gav
delo malu, if the beard fills out even if it's not three
months, מלו ג' חודשים, malu gimel chodashim, דלא מלו ג' חודשים, delo
malu gimel chodashim, excuse me, or מלו ג' חודשים אף על גב
דלא הקיף, malu gimel chodashim af al gav delo hikif, whichever one
comes first. Fine. And we now we know the reasons why, why
the filling out, he's no longer just at the cusp of, he's
not a בן that's just at the cusp of being a man,
he's a full man. And after three months, he's already ראוי להכריסו
אב. ra'uy lehachriso av.
Okay. יתיב רב יעקב מנהר פקוד קמיה דרבינא. yativ rav yaakov min
d'har pakod kamei d'ravina. Rav Yaakov from d'Har Pakod was sitting in
front of Ravina. ויתיב וקאמר משמיה דרב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, veyativ
vekamar mishmei derav huna brei derav yehoshua, and saying in the name
of Rav Huna, the son of Rav Yehoshua, שמע מינה מדרב כוספאי.
shema mina miderav kuspai. We can learn now from the teaching of
Rav Kuspai, אמר רב שבתאי, יולדת לשבעה אין עוברה ניכר לשליש ימיה.
yoledet leshiva ein ubra nikar leshlish yameha. From this, that that a
woman who...
so let's learn now from this statement that Rav Kuspai says in
the name of Rav Shaptai that we said earlier that it's only
three months, the time of a בן סורר ומורה, ben sorer u'moreh
that from that we can infer that כל ימיו של בן סורר
ומורה אינו אלא ג' חודשים בלבד. kol yamav shel ben sorer umoreh
eino ela gimel chodashim bilvad.
I'm sorry, skipped a line.
שמע מינה מדרב כוספאי אמר רב שבתאי יולדת לשבעה אין עוברה ניכר
לשליש ימיה. shema mina miderav kuspai amar rav shaptai yoledet leshiva ein
ubra nikar leshlish yameha. That if a woman were to give birth
in the seventh month, or after seven months, because the גמרא Gemara
understood that, you know, a... the גמרא Gemara had a funny understanding
that you could give birth like at the end of nine months
and at the end of seven months but not like in your
eighth month, that that actually the child would not survive, but that's
a whole different discussion. But that when a woman does give birth
in seven months, that you would not say that the fetus would
be visible, because, you know, in a third of that time. By
a normal nine-month pregnancy, we say the fetus is visible in three
months. So what would happen in the seven-month pregnancy? Would the fetus
be visible, would everything be speeded up, would the fetus be visible
in two and a third months or would it only be visible
in three months? So from the teaching of Rav Kuspai in the
name of Rav Shaptai, you can, you can figure out that even
in the case of a seven-month pregnancy, the fetus is not visible
at a third of the time, but only after three full months.
How do you figure that out? דאי סלקא דעתך עובר ניכר לשליש
ימיו, de'ei salka dachatech ubar nikar leshlish yamav, because if in that
case the fetus would be visible after a third of the time,
so it would be parallel, you know, the same proportion of time
as a nine-month pregnancy, so למה לי ג'? lama li gimel? Why
would the days of a בן סורר ומורה only be, you know,
why would they be limited to three months? בתרי ותילתא סגי. bitrei
vetilta sagi. His window should only be two and a third. After
two and a third months, a בן סורר ומורה is ראוי להכריסו
אב. ra'uy lehachriso av. Theoretically, he could be a father. He could
have impregnated somebody the day he became Bar Mitzvah and it could
have been a case of a seven-month pregnancy and it would have
been visible in two and a third months and that would be
a time when it's already fit to call him a father. So
since we make the window three months, you see that no matter
if the pregnancy is a nine-month pregnancy or a seven-month pregnancy, the
woman will only be, you know, visible that she's pregnant, will only
be showing after three months. Okay, that seems like a pretty good
argument. אמר ליה. amar lei. He said back, לעולם אימא לך עובר
ניכר לשליש ימיו. le'olam eima lach ubar nikar leshlish yamav. I can
tell you no, in the seven-month pregnancy the fetus is visible in
a third of the time, in two and a third months. But
why then did we say that the בן סורר ומורה is a
three-month window and not a two and a third months window? זיל
בתר רובא. zil batar ruba. Because you go by the majority when
you're trying to figure out when is the time when it's fit
to call him a father. You say in most circumstances, he would
not be able to be called a father until, you know, until
three months. So even though there's exceptions to that rule, you would
define that period of ראוי להכריסו, ra'uy lehachriso, you know, that of
when he's still a בן and not fit to be a father
to extend for a full three months. You go by the majority.
So, זיל בתר רובא. zil batar ruba. אהדרוה קמיה דרבינא. ahadruha kamei
deravina. So they, you know, brought this answer back to Ravina.
אמר להו. amar lehu. And he said to them, ובדיני נפשות אזלינן
בתר רובא? uvdinei nefashot azlinan batar ruba? I'm sorry, I skipped a
line again.
זיל בתר רובא. zil batar ruba. אהדרוה קמיה דרב הונא בריה דרב
יהושע. ahadruha kamei derav huna brei derav yehoshua. So they said this
answer in front of Rav Huna, the son of Rav Yehoshua. אמר
להו. amar lehu. And he said back to them, ובדיני נפשות מי
אזלינן בתר רובא? uvdinei nefashot mi azlinan batar ruba? Why should we
go by רוב? rov? Right? We should, it, this is a case
of a capital crime, בן סורר ומורה, and therefore we should try
to limit the ability to apply it. A life is at stake.
It's a capital crime and we should not go by majority and
we should say since it's possible to be a father, to be
called a father at two and a third months, that should determine
to make the window even smaller. והתורה אמרה, ve'hatorah amrah, and the
תורה Torah said, ושפטו העדה והצילו העדה, v'shafetu ha'eda vehitzilu ha'eda, that
you have an obligation to try to save the person. Now, of
course, until now we've been dealing with that in the context of
the deliberations, but here it is sort of applying it even in
the context of the criteria to be fit. finding somebody guilty and
the שיעורים shiurim and of course we know that חזל chazal require
witnesses and warning and the guy saying I don't care. So here
it's saying we should not go even when we're deciding the שיעור
shiur of when is it fit to call him a father, you
know, when is he still able and you know when is he
still not fit, we should try to define that period of בן
סורר ומורה as small as possible and not go by רוב. rov.
ואת אמרת זיל בתר רובא, ve'at amart zil batar ruba, you're saying
we should go by רוב? rov? אזלו קמיה דרבינא, azlu kamei d'Ravina,
so they went and they gave, they you know were sort of
shuttling the back and forth between you know between Ravina and Rav
Huna here. So they said back they said Ravina, here Rav Huna
says you shouldn't go by רוב, rov, you should try even you
should go by the minority to try to shorten the window. אמר
ליה amar lei and Ravina said back, בדיני נפשות לא אזלינן בתר
רובא bedinei nefashot lo azlinan batar ruba what? Do you think we
don't go by רוב rov by בדיני נפשות, dinei nefashot, by capital
crimes? But we do. והתנן v'hatnan we taught in the Mishnah, אחד
אומר בשנים בחדש ואחד אומר בשלשה עדותן קיימת. echad omer bishnayim bachodesh
v'echad omer bishlosha eydutan kayemet. If one person says that this guy
killed somebody on the second of the month, the other says it
was on the third of the month, you don't say that they're
contradicting, you say that they're actually testifying to the same thing. שזה
יודע
בעיבורו של חודש וזה אינו יודע shezeh yodeia b'ibura shel chodesh v'zeh
eino yodeia because this one knows that it was a full month,
month before, and the other one doesn't. So you know it's possible
that people are off by one day in terms of what day
of the month it is based on how long the month was
before and you don't always know at the beginning of the month,
you know maybe they didn't get the news from בית דין. Beit
Din. ואי סלקא דעתך לא אמרינן זיל בתר רובא v'ee salka da'atach
lo amrinan zil batar ruba if you were to say we never
go by majority in capital crimes because we're always looking for any
excuse to get the guy off, so נימא הני דוקא קמסהדי neima
hanei davka kamasahadi why don't we say that the witnesses are actually
are saying are accurate, not that one of them is off, ואכחושי
הוא דקמכחשי אהדדי v'achshishei hu d'kamachashishi ahadadi and they're contradicting one another.
אלא לאו משום דאמרינן זיל בתר רובא ורובא דאינשי עבדי דטעו בעיבורא
דירחא ella lav mishum d'amrinan zil batar ruba v'ruba d'inshi abdei d'ta'u
b'ibura d'yarcha it must be that no, even by בדיני נפשות dinei
nefashot we go by majority and we say that it's very likely,
it's very common that people make a mistake in terms of when
ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh was and therefore we don't look at this
as a contradiction. Okay, so you know now this is a little
bit different, I mean they're all sort of the same, right? It's
not like that we say if there's the evidence, the preponderance of
the evidence, the majority, it's 51 percent likely or even 70 percent
likely he killed somebody, we're going to kill him, right? That's not
what we're, you know, we're going to execute him. That's not what
we're saying in זיל בתר רובא. zil batar ruba. The זיל בתר
רובא zil batar ruba here is more sort of about like setting
up the parameters,
what to define the period of time when he's not fit to
be called a father, go by the majority. What should be defined
when you say witnesses contradict one another? Only if you know they're
clearly contradicting, but if it's understandable that people might make a mistake
and otherwise everything else they're saying is the same thing, then that
doesn't define a contradiction. Okay, so those types of things you can
use the idea of רוב. rov. Okay.
אמר רבי ירמיה מדיפתי אף אנן נמי תנינא, amar Rabbi Yirmiyah miDifti
af anan nami tanina, we also taught in the Mishnah, בת שלש
שנים ויום אחד מתקדשת בביאה. bat shalosh shanim v'yom echad miskadeshet b'biah.
So we've taught this earlier in the מסכת. masechet. It's also משנה
נדה, Mishnah Niddah, if a girl is three years old then she
could be married off by her father through ביאה, biah, meaning it's
considered an act of intercourse and it works for קדושין. kiddushin. ואם
בא עליה יבם קנה v'im ba aleha yavam kanah
and if the brother-in-law, you know, an act of יבום yibum was
done where it's effected through an act of intercourse then that is
effective once she's three years and a day. וחייבין עליה משום אשת
איש v'chayavin aleha mishum eshet ish and if she was married either
through יבום yibum or through ביאה biah or through any means and
then somebody had intercourse with her, he would be חייב chayav for
intercourse with a married woman, it would be an act of intercourse
and he'd be put to death. ומטמא את בועלה לטמא משכב תחתון
כעליון umitamei et bo'alah letamei mishkav tachton k'elyon if she's a נדה
niddah then the one who has intercourse with a נדה niddah is
טמא, tamei, he becomes like her, an אב הטומאה av hatumah not
just like somebody who touched a נדה niddah and this is defined
as an act of intercourse and he becomes an אב הטומאה av
hatumah and even the things that he is sitting on, the top
thing and the bottom thing, and if he's sitting on ten cushions,
even the bottom one becomes טמא, tamei, it's like the law of
a משכב mishkav of a נדה niddah except it's one degree removed.
We won't go into that detail right now. ניסת לכהן אוכלת בתרומה,
nisset l'kohen ochelet b'terumah, if she's married to a כהן kohen she
can eat תרומה terumah because you know for a woman to eat
תרומה terumah married to a כהן kohen at least rabbinically you require
that it be חופה, chuppah, it be fit to have ביאה, biah,
and so since she's fit to have ביאה biah she can eat
from תרומה. terumah. בא עליה אחד מן הפסולים פסל מן הכהונה ba
aleha echad min hapsulin pasal min hakehunah
if she has intercourse from somebody who is invalid for a כהן
kohen like a חלל chalal or a ממזר mamzer or whatever then
that makes her invalid to marry a כהן. kohen. ואם בא עליה
אחד מכל העריות המתות בתורה v'im ba aleha echad micol ha'arayot hamitot
batorah and if any one of the forbidden you know עריות arayot
has intercourse with her, הומתו עליה והיא פטורה. humatu aleha v'hi peturah.
They would be put to death for cause of her because you
know it's intercourse, again if it was a brother, a father, what,
well not brother that's not חייב מיתה chayav mita whatever, anyway, a
father, a case of a married, you know, she was a married
woman etc., they would be put to death, she would be exempt
obviously that she's a minor. Okay, we've seen all of that before,
three years and a day is considered an act of intercourse. How
is this relevant to us? So let's take a look here at
the top of ס"ט עמוד ב. Sam-Tes Amud Beis.
ואמאי Ve'amai why is this true? אימא Eima אילין אישי ilin ishi
ודעתא דהכי לא קדשי. Vedaita dehachi lo kadeshi. So why do we
consider her to be a married woman and when her father marries
her off and the man who has intercourse with her is חייב
chayav because of אשת איש aishes ish because of adultery, you know,
if it turns out that she is an אילונית aylonis which is
somebody who is not only infertile but basically has like male
characteristics—we won't go into exactly what it is right now—but under those
circumstances we say that it was a קידושי טעות, kiddushei taus, so
it might turn out that the wedding will be a קידושי טעות
kiddushei taus and we're not concerned with that. We say that that
will be a rare exception and by default we should assume that
it is what it looks like, which is that the קידושין kiddushin
is good. And we're not going to worry about some future thing
which might make us revise our assumption right now. ודעתא דהכי לא
קידש Vedaita dehachi lo kidesh and he didn't marry if she were
to turn out to be an אילונית. aylonis. אלא לאו דאמרינן זיל
בתר רובא Ela lav de'amrinan zil basar ruba you see that even
by דיני נפשות dinei nefashos we go by רוב. rov. Again, רוב
rov that let us assume the basic parameters are as we see
them and we don't have to worry about some of those other
possibilities. ורוב נשי לאו אילונית נינהו Verov nashi lav aylonis ninhu and
most of them are not an אילונית. aylonis. So that seems to
be another good proof to that. So הגמרא ha'gemara says לא. מאי
חייב עליה דקתני קרבן. Mai chayav aleha de'katni korban. No, no, no,
when it says you're חייב chayav it doesn't mean that we would
execute somebody; it means they bring a קרבן korban if it was
שוגג. shogeg. So הגמרא ha'gemara says you can't say that. והא מותן
על ידה קתני. Veha musan al yadah katni. It says that they
are executed for her so we're talking about actually דיני נפשות. dinei
nefashos. בבא על אביה. Be'va al avia. No,
we're not talking about a case of קידושין kiddushin maybe we would
say she might not be מקודשת mekudeshes because it'll turn out to
be קידושי טעות. kiddushei taus. We're talking about a case that her
father had intercourse with her and it's a case of one of
עריות arayos of, you know, incest. So הגמרא ha'gemara says no והא
מבוא על אחת מכל העריות קתני. veha mibo al achas mikol ha'arayos
katni. It says if any one of the עריות—actually arayos they could
also refer to earlier in המשנה hamishna where it said אשת איש—anyway,
aishes ish so clearly we're including a case of marriage and you
see we're not worried that she might turn out to be an
אילונית. aylonis. Okay, so this is interesting because we're saying we do
go by דיני נפשות dinei nefashos after רוב, rov, but you might
remember there's סוגיא sugia in בבא קמא Bava Kamma whatever that we
don't even go by דיני ממונות dinei mamonos after רוב. rov. So
how could you not go by דיני ממונות dinei mamonos after רוב
rov but you could go by דיני נפשות? dinei nefashos? Right, obviously
you should protect life more than you protect money. But part of
the answer is that this is where we're just setting basic parameters.
You know, it's not considered a הכחשה hakhasha if people normally make
a mistake. It's so when we want to define what is the
period you're fit to be called a son and not fit to
be called a father, we'll define it by a majority. Somebody had
a קידושין, kiddushin, we're going to go by that definition right now
and not worry that a small chance that something in the future
might cause us to reassess.
Okay. So הגמרא ha'gemara says אלא, but הגמרא ha'gemara has this still
a way to get out of this. הכא במאי עסקינן דקיבלה ליה.
Hacha be'mai askinan de'kiblei lei. No, maybe we're talking about that he
explicitly said I'm marrying you even if you turn out to be
an אילונית. aylonis. So you can't prove from this that we go
by רוב; rov; it might be a case where he explicitly says
I'm willing to accept it even if it turns out to be
to be otherwise. Okay. תנו רבנן Tano rabanan our rabbis taught. המסוללת
בפני בנה קטן Hamisuleles biphnei bna katan
if a woman is מסוללת, misuleles, you know, that's a phrase that
could be used, you know, in a very—רש"י Rashi says לשון פריצות—specifically
lashon pritzus like engaging in sexual behavior; it could just mean sort
of, you know, very close intimate physical contact, maybe it doesn't mean
that it was intentionally sexual, but one way or the other, a
woman is being like naked together with her minor son. והערה בו
Ve'hera bo and he went ahead and he penetrated her—העראה ha'ara'a is
just the just barely penetrated, just inserting of the tip of the
penis. בית שמאי אומרים פסולה מן הכהונה Beis Shammai omrim pasula min
hakehuna she's now is invalid to marry a כהן, kohein, right, even
if she was a case where whatever her husband were to die
and she would be an אלמנה almuna or maybe she's not even
married now, anyway she now has had intercourse with her son and
that makes her that invalidates her for a כהן. kohein. בית הלל
מכשירין Beis Hillel makhshirin and בית הלל Beis Hillel says no
she's still כשר. kosher. Why could that be? I mean, she actually
did have intercourse and, you know, with somebody who is—what do you
call it?—which would invalidate her. Ah, but the question is how old
is the son? By we've been saying that, you know, it's only
considered an act of intercourse with the boy once he's nine years
old. So now הגמרא ha'gemara is going to try to explain what
their debate is. אמר רבי חייא בריה דרבה בר נחמני אמר רב
חסדא ואמרי לה אמר רב חסדא אמר זעירי Amar Rabbi Chiya brei
de'Rava bar Nachmani amar Rav Chisda ve'amre lah amar Rav Chisda amar
Ze'iri הכל מודים בבן תשע שנים ויום אחד hakol modim be'ven tesha
shanim ve'yom echad so these various אמוראים amoraim say
everybody would agree that once the son was nine years and one
day שביאתו ביאה she'biaso bia
that that's an act of intercourse and, you know, and whether it
was intentional or non-intentional
she's now invalid to a כהן. kohein. פחות מבן שמונה Pachus miben
shmona שאין ביאתו ביאה she'ein biaso bia and everybody else agrees that
under eight years old it's not an act of intercourse. לא נחלקו
אלא בבן שמונה Lo nekhleku ela be'ven shmona the debate is eight
years old and a day until nine. Nine years old and a
day, okay, the בית שמאי סברי Beis Shammai savri גמינא מדורות הראשונים
gamina midoros harishonim ובית הלל סברי u'Beis Hillel savri לא גמינא מדורות
הראשונים. lo gamina midoros harishonim. בית שמאי Beis Shammai says we learn
from earlier generations, the גמרא's Gemara going to show how we can
infer from certain פסוקים pesukim that even an eight year old child
in the past could have actually, this is going to get back
to the issue of father children, but we're going to see even
an eight year old child could father children, so therefore it would
be considered an act of intercourse certainly.
And בית שמאי Beis Shammai says we learn from that example, and
בית הלל Beis Hillel says we don't learn from that example. Right
now, you know, we go by our מציאות metzius right now, whatever
was in the past was in the past. You know, in the
biblical times they lived hundreds of years also, so and that's not
going to define for us. For us it's going to be nine
years and a day. But as we said, it will be interesting
because the גמרא Gemara will at least say that certainly at least
in the past, not only eight years and a day was an
act of intercourse, but actually could father a child. Okay, it's actually
a little bit strange that this seems to be that the גמרא
Gemara is framing the debate about eight years and a day to
nine years, because then why is it given specifically in this context
of a mother who's, you know, being like intimate with her son?
Why didn't it just talk about the regular debate of when is
the act of sex of an under-age boy considered an act of
sex? But that's the way the גמרא Gemara is choosing to frame
the debate. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, ודורות
ראשונים מנלן דאוליד, Vedoros rishonim minalan de'olid, where do you know that
the earlier generations gave birth at eight years old? אילימא דכתיב הלוא
זאת בת שבע בת אליעם אשת אוריה החתי, Ileima dechsiv halo zos
Batsheva bas Eliam eshes Uriya Hachiti,
so here בת שבע Batsheva is the daughter of אליעם, Eliam, the
wife of אוריה החתי. Uriya Hachiti. וכתיב אליעם בן אחיתפל הגילני, Uchsiv
Eliam ben Achitofel Hagiloni, so אליעם Eliam was the
father, was the son of אחיתופל, Achitofel, so בת שבע Batsheva is
the granddaughter of אחיתופל. Achitofel. וכתיב וישלח ביד נתן הנביא ויקרא שמו
ידידיה בעבור ה' אבו, Uchsiv vayishlach beyad Nasan Hanavi vayikra shemo Yedidya
ba'avur Hashem avo, okay,
and this is, you know, talking about the birth of שלמה Shlomo
who was called ידידיה Yedidya
because God, ידיד ה', Yedid Hashem, God loved him, that was born
to בת שבע. Batsheva. וכתיב ויהי לשנתים ימים ויהיו גזזים לאבשלום. Uchsiv
vayehi lishnasayim yamim vayiheyu gozezim le-Avshalom.
So now we're going to see, we're going to sort of try
to, we'll be stringing פסוקים pesukim together to show that שלמה Shlomo
who was born to בת שבע, Batsheva, who we see was the
granddaughter
of אחיתופל, Achitofel, so we're going to see that שלמה Shlomo was
seven years old when אחיתופל Achitofel died and we'll see the age
of אחיתופל Achitofel and that'll sort of lead us back to figuring
out when אחיתופל Achitofel had children. So just sort of hold on
and follow me here. Okay, so וכתיב ויהי לשנתים ימים, Uchsiv vayehi
lishnasayim yamim, so two years after שלמה Shlomo was born, ויהיו גזזים
לאבשלום. vayiheyu gozezim le-Avshalom. וכתיב אבשלום ברח וילך גשור ויהי שם שלוש
שנים, Uchsiv Avshalom barach vayelech Geshur vayehi sham shalosh shanim, and then
אבשלום Avshalom ran away, you know, whatever the whole thing was with
fighting for the chair, for the throne, anyway, three years. So now
שלמה Shlomo was five years old in this, you know, as we're
stringing together the years mentioned in the various narratives. וכתיב וישב אבשלום
בירושלים שנתים ימים ופני המלך לא ראה, Uchsiv vayeshev Avshalom bi-Yerushalayim she-nasayim
yamim upenei hamelech lo ra'ah, and then he came back and he
was brought back and he didn't see his father King דוד David
for two years. So now anyway שלמה Shlomo was seven years old.
וכתיב ויהי מקץ ארבעים שנה, Uchsiv vayehi miketz arba'im shana, and it
was after forty years. Okay, that's for the forty years from the
time they asked for a king, not forty years from our chronology,
so bracket the forty years. ויאמר אבשלום אל המלך אלכה נא ואשלם
את נדרי אשר נדרתי לה' בחברון. Vayomer Avshalom el hamelech elcha na
va'ashalem es nidri asher nadarti l'Hashem be-Hevron. וכתיב ואחיתפל ראה כי לא
נעשתה עצתו, Uchsiv v'Achitofel ra'ah ki lo na'asa atzaso,
so anyway, here it was that after the seven years and אבשלום
Avshalom was back to ירושלים Yerushalayim and now אחיתופל Achitofel saw that
his plan, his whole plan had not, was not done. I don't
want to get into all the whole narrative here the תנ"ך. Tanakh.
ויחבש את החמור ויקם וילך אל ביתו, Vayachavosh es hachamor vayakam vayelech
el beiso, he saddled up his donkey, he went to his house,
ואל עירו ויצו אל ביתו Ve-el iro vayetzav el beiso and he,
you know, he gave his final orders, ויחנק vayichanek and he strangled
himself. Okay, so the key is שלמה Shlomo was seven years old
when אחיתופל Achitofel died, committed suicide. וכתיב, Uchsiv, now how old was
אחיתופל? Achitofel? אנשי דמים ומרמה
לא יחצו ימיהם, Anshei damim u-mirma lo yechetzu yemeihem, people, you know,
men of blood and deceit, they won't live half their days. ותניא
כל שנותיו של דואג אינם אלא שלושים וארבע, Ve-sanya kol shnosav shel
Doeg einam ela sheloshim ve-arba, so from person, ימי שנותינו בהם שבעים
שנה, yemei shnoseinu bahem shiv'im shana, if seventy years was considered the
norm, so they don't get the half, they don't get to thirty-five.
So we have a tradition that דואג Doeg who also man of
deceit and blood lived only to thirty-four years old. ושל אחיתפל איניש
שלושים ושלוש, Veshel Achitofel enish sheloshim ve-shalosh, and אחיתופל's Achitofel thirty-three. So
that's the key, אחיתופל Achitofel died at the age of thirty-three when
שלמה Shlomo was seven years old. כמה הוו להו? Kama havyu lehu?
תלתא ותלתא, Tlasa ve-tlasa, he was thirty-three. דל שבע דהוי שלמה, Dal
shiva d'havé Shlomo,
שלמה Shlomo was seven years old when that happened. So now subtract
seven, so we're twenty-six. אחיתופל Achitofel was twenty-six when his granddaughter בת
שבע Batsheva gave birth to שלמה. Shlomo. Okay, דהוי שלמה... d'havé Shlomo...
פשו עשרין ושית, pashu esrin ve-shis, twenty-six. דל תרתי שני לתלתא עיבורי,
Dal tartei shnei l'slasa iburei, and, you
know, for the pregnancies, you know, there has to be if אחיתופל
Achitofel gave birth to אליעם Eliam and אליעם Eliam gave birth to
First Bat Sheva, were birthed, and Bat Sheva gave birth to Shlomo,
so that's three births that happened there, and that's three, so that's
three nine-month periods, that's more or less, you know, two years. So
subtract two years from the three pregnancies, אשתכח, ishtakach,
so now we're down to 24. אשתכח דחד וחד בתמני אוליד, ishtakach
dechad vechad betamnei olid,
each generation gave birth at eight. Okay, Achitophel at eight years old,
you know, impregnated a woman, when he was nine roughly, you know,
she gave birth to Eliam his son. Eliam when he was eight
and Achitophel was 17, impregnated a woman, you know, when now Achitophel
is 18, his son was born, Bat Sheva was born, then, you
know, eight, then Bat Sheva was eight, so now according to this
Bat Sheva was eight when David saw whatever, you know, and, and
then, and then got pregnant and gave birth and then got pregnant
for, you know, for a year and gave birth when she was
nine and Achitophel was 26. And then that means that he was
33 when he committed suicide. Okay, so each generation there either sired
a child or gave birth to a child at eight months? All
right,
where were we? דחד וחד בתמני אוליד. dechad vechad betamnei olid.
So the Gemara says ממאי, mimay, how do you know that? דילמא
תרוייהו בתשע אוליד, dilma revayhu betisha olid, maybe the two men in
that chain
sired at nine years old, because our focus is on the men,
ובת שבע לאו בשית, u'Vat Sheva lav beshit, and Bat Sheva gave
birth at six years, right? So our, so maybe men it took
them till nine years, but Bat Sheva was even younger, and then
when you add them up, you still get to your 24. משום
דאיתתא בריא mishum d'itit'ba
because a woman is more strong than men. תדע דהא הוי ולד
מעיקרא teda deha havi velad me'ikara because
Bat Sheva anyway, there was a child that died before Shlomo. So
it's not going to work anyway, it's going to get even younger
than eight. So you're going to have to say that Bat Sheva
was very young and then you could say that the two men
in this equation were both nine years old.
Okay, so the Gemara now tries to learn it out from another
passage in the Tanakh. אלא מהכא. ela mehacha. Let's learn it out
from here. אלה תולדות תרח תרח הוליד את אברם את נחור ואת
הרן. Eileh toldot Terach, Terach holid et Avram, et Nachor, v'et Haran.
All right, so we all know that. ואברם גדול מנחור שנה ונחור
גדול מהרן שנה. v'Avram gadol mi'Nachor shana, v'Nachor gadol mi'Haran shana. So
we're going to assume that these are being listed in age order,
so Avram was and somehow we're assuming that they're only one year
apart or maybe that's where the minimum assumption. Okay, so Haran is
two years younger than Avram. ונמצא אברם גדול שתי שנים מהרן, venimtza
Avram gadol shtei shanim mi'Haran,
so he's two years older than Haran. וכתיב ויקח אברם ונחור להם
נשים, u'chtiv vayikach Avram v'Nachor lahem nashim, and they took wives, שם
אשת אברם שרי ושם אשת נחור מלכה בת הרן אבי מלכה ואבי
יסכה. shem eshet Avram Sarai v'shem eshet Nachor Milkah bat Haran avi
Milkah v'avi Yiskah.
So the end of that pasuk is that we know that יסכה
Yiskah was a daughter of הרן, Haran, Avram's brother. ואמר רבי יצחק
יסכה זו שרה, ve'amar Rabbi Yitzchak Yiskah zo Sarah, and Yiskah is
associated with Sarah, I mean also, you know, like why else is
the Torah telling us its name so you can understand why Chazal
want to identify her with Sarah. ולמה נקרא שמה יסכה שסוכה ברוח
הקודש, velama nikra shema Yiskah, shesocha beruach hakodesh,
that she could see with the Ruach HaKodesh. Okay, so now we
have Avram is married to Haran's daughter. Sarah is Haran's daughter. והיינו
דכתיב כל אשר תאמר אליך שרה שמע בקולה. v'hainu dechtiv kol asher
tomar eilecha Sarah shema bekola.
And that's why you have to listen to Sarah because she was,
she had Nevuah, she had Ruach HaKodesh, even greater than Avram according
to them. Okay. דבר אחר יסכה שהכל סוכין ביופיה. davar acher Yiskah
shehakol sochin beyofyah. Or Yiskah to mean to look, but not that
she looks with Ruach HaKodesh, but everybody looks at her beauty. Okay,
fine. So Sarah is יסכה, Yiskah, Sarah is the daughter of הרן,
Haran, Avram's younger brother by two years. ויפל אברם על פניו ויצחק
ויאמר בלבו. vayipol Avram al panav vayitzchak vayomer belibo. Okay. הלבן מאה
שנה יולד ואם שרה בת תשעים שנה תלד. haleven meah shana ivaled
v'im Sarah bat tishim shana teleid.
So Avram was 100 and Sarah was 90. כמה קשיש אברם משרה
עשר שנים, kama kashish Avram mi'Sarah eser shanim, so he's 10 years
older than Sarah. וקשיש מאבוה תרתין שנים, v'kashish me'avuha tartein shanim,
and he is two years older than Sarah's father, right? He's the
oldest son, he's two years older than Haran, and he's 10 years
older than Sarah. Okay. אשתכח כי אולדה הרן לשרה בתמני אולידה, ishtakach
ki olda Haran le'Sarah betamnei olida, so if that's true, when Haran
sired Sarah, Haran had to be eight years old. Because why?
Because
he
was eight years old, and Avram at that age would have been
10, and Sarah would be born, so there you have Avram 10
years older than Sarah. Actually it's a little bit of a problem
because it means he got his wife pregnant at seven, but okay
maybe we're being a little like nine months, we're not being exact.
Anyway, so the Gemara says like this: ממאי. mimay. How do you
know that's how the math works? דילמא אברהם זוטא דאחוה הוה. Dilma
Avraham zuta de-achu hava. Maybe Haran was the older brother and Avraham
was the younger brother and we don't know how many years older
Haran was, so you can't learn anything from how old Haran was
when he gave birth to, when he sired Sarah. ודרך חכמתם קחשיב
להו, Ve-derech chochmatam kachashev lehu,
and the Torah is enumerating them, Avraham is listed first not because
he's the oldest, but because he is the wisest or the most
important. תדע דקחשיב להו כדרך חכמתם דכתיב, Teda dekachashev lehu kederech chochmatam
dechtiv,
and we know sometimes the פסוקים psukim list children not in order
of their age but in order of their wisdom or in order
of their stature, as it says, ויהי נח בן חמש מאות שנה
ויולד נח את שם את חם ואת יפת. Vayehi Noach ben chamesh
meot shana vayoled Noach et Shem et Cham ve-et Yafet. שם גדול
מחם שנה וחם גדול מיפת שנה. Shem gadol mi-Cham shana ve-Cham gadol
mi-Yafet shana. So if we're going to assume age order, Shem is
one year older and we're somehow going to assume sequential like we
did before, Shem is one year older than Cham, Cham one year
older than Yafet. נמצא שם גדול מיפת שתי שנים. Nimtza Shem gadol
mi-Yafet shtei shanim. Just like we said by Avraham and Haran. וכתיב
נח בן שש מאות שנה והמבול היה מים
על הארץ. U-chtiv Noach ben shesh meot shana ve-ha-mabul haya mayim al
ha-aretz. Noach was six hundred. וכתיב, U-chtiv, and we know Noach gave
birth when he was five hundred years old to Shem and then
Cham and then Yafet. וכתיב אלה תולדות שם שם בן מאה שנה
ויולד את ארפכשד שנתיים אחר המבול. U-chtiv eleh toldot Shem, Shem ben
mea shana vayoled et Arpachshad shnatayim achar ha-mabul. Shem was
a hundred years and he gave birth to Arpachshad two years after
the מבול. mabul. So it sounds like he was ninety-eight at the
time of the מבול. mabul. But according
if we assume that Noach gave birth to them in order, Shem
was born when Noach was five hundred, then Shem and Noach was,
that was when Noach was five hundred and the מבול mabul was
when Noach was six hundred, then Shem should have been a hundred
years old. אחר המבול בן מאה שנה, Achar ha-mabul ben mea shana,
what do you mean he was a hundred years old? I mean
a hundred years old when the מבול mabul was over and a
hundred and two, two years after the מבול. mabul. בר מאה ותרין
שנין הוי. Bar mea ve-tartin shnin havei. אלא דרך חכמתם קחשיב להו,
Ela derech chochmatam kachashev lehu, so when it says Shem, Cham, and
Yafet, it's not listing them in the order of their birth order
but in the order of their stature. הכא נמי דרך חכמתם קחשיב
להו, Hacha nami derech chochmatam kachashev lehu, here too by Avraham and
Haran. So you cannot have it that even if יסכה Iscah is
Sarah, you cannot say that Avraham was older and that Haran had
to have her, she was born when Haran her father was eight
years old. That you cannot prove because Haran might have been older
than Avraham. אמר רב כהנא אמריתה לשמעתא קמיה דרב זביד, Amar Rav
Kahana amrita le-shmata kamei de-Rav Zvid, so we haven't really proved that
דורות ראשונים dorot rishonim gave birth at, sired at eight years old.
אמר רב כהנא אמריתה לשמעתא קמיה דרב זביד מנהרדעא אמר לי אתון
מהכא מתניתו ואנן מהכא מתנינא, Amar Rav Kahana amrita le-shmata kamei de-Rav
Zvid mi-Nehardea amar li atun mehacha matnitu ve-anan mehacha matnina, you try
to prove it from those פסוקים psukim and
here's how we bring it from. ולשם יולד גם הוא אבי כל
בני עבר אחי יפת הגדול. U-le-Shem yulad gam hu avi kol bnei
Ever achi Yafet ha-gadol. Shem was born to him, the father of
all those from the other side of the river, Ever, the brother
of Yafet the elder. יפת הגדול שבאחיו הוה, Yafet ha-gadol she-be-achav hava,
and so now אחי יפת הגדול, achi Yafet ha-gadol, it sounds like,
maybe הגדול ha-gadol could refer to Shem but the simple sense is
Yafet the older one. So look from over there, we don't see
here from here the eight years old. From over here is where
we see also that Shem, Cham, and Yafet are not listed in
order because the later פסוק pasuk says יפת הגדול. Yafet ha-gadol. So
we cannot prove that this idea based on the names that they're
listed, that that's the birth order. So we're still, we still don't
know that they gave birth at eight years old.
אלא מנלן, Ela menalan, so where do you know it? From מהכא,
mehacha, from here. ובצלאל בן אורי בן חור למטה יהודה. U-Vetzalel ben
Uri ben Chur le-mateh Yehuda. Vetzalel was the son of Uri the
son of
Chur. וכתיב ותמת עזובה, U-chtiv va-tamot Azuva, so Azuva died, ויקח לו
כלב את אפרת ותלד לו את חור. Vayikach lo Kalev et Efrat
vateled lo et Chur. So Chur now we are going to find
out is the son of
Caleb. Vetzalel was בן אורי בן חור ben Uri ben Chur and
Chur was the son of Caleb. וכי עבד בצלאל משכן בר כמה
הוי בר תליסר. Ve-chi avad Vetzalel mishkan bar kama havei bar tlisar.
When Vetzalel made the Mishkan, he had to be at least
thirteen. דכתיב איש איש ממלאכתו אשר הם עושים. De-chtiv ish ish mi-melachto
asher hem osim. ותניא, Ve-tanya, שנה ראשונה עשה משה משכן שניה הקים
משכן ושלח מרגלים. Shana rishona asa Moshe Mishkan shniya hekim Mishkan ve-shalach
meraglim. First year he made the Mishkan, second year they sent the
מרגלים. meraglim. וכתיב, U-chtiv, so Vetzalel would be minimum fourteen years old
when the מרגלים meraglim were sent.
וכתיב בן ארבעים שנה אנכי בשלח משה עבד ה'. U-chtiv ben arbaim
shana anochi bi-shloach Moshe eved Hashem. Then the פסוק pasuk also says
that Caleb says I was forty years when he was sent as
the
מרגל. meragel. ועתה הנה אנכי היום בן חמש ושמונים שנה. Ve-ata hineh
anochi ha-yom ben chamesh u-shmonim shana. כמה הוו להו ארבעין. Kama havu
lehu arbain. So he was forty years when he was sent as
the מרגל. meragel. דל ארבע עשרה דהוה בצלאל, Dal arba esreh de-hava
Vetzalel, minus fourteen that was Vetzalel, Vetzalel was born fourteen years before.
So fourteen years earlier when Caleb was twenty-six, Vetzalel was born. פשו
להו עשרים ושית. Pashu lehu esrim ve-shis. דל תרתי שני דתלתא עיבורי.
Dal tarti shnei de-tlata iburei. Now we're going to have to go
from Caleb would have to have Chur, Chur would have to have...
אורי, Uri, אורי Uri would have to have בצלאל. Bezalel. That's three
births, so three births, nine months per birth, that's minus two years
like we did before.
So where are we? Hold on. דל י"ד דהוה בצלאל, Dal yod-daled
de'hava Bezalel, פשו ליה עשרין ושיש. pashu lei esrin v'shish. דל תרתי
שני דתלתא עיבורי, Dal tartei shnei d'tlasa iburei, so subtract two years
for the three pregnancies. אשתכח דכל חד וחד בתמני אוליד. Ishtakach de'kol
chad v'chad bitamnei aolid. So each one gave birth at eight years
old, right? Because then you have בצלאל Bezalel to אורי, Uri, אורי
Uri to חור, Chur, excuse me, כלב Calev to חור, Chur, חור
Chur to אורי, Uri, אורי Uri to בצלאל. Bezalel. And all of
that has to be done in 24 years. So each one was
eight years old. That is the debate of בית הלל, Beis Hillel,
בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, do we learn from דורות הראשונים doros harishonim
or not? Okay, back to the משנה. בן ולא בת. Ben v'lo
bas. So בן סורר ומורה could only be a boy, not a
girl. תניא, Tanya, we taught in the ברייתא, braitisa, אמר רבי שמעון,
amar Rebi Shimon, בדין הוא שתהא בת ראויה להיות כבן סורר ומורה.
b'din hu she'tei bas re'uya lihyos k'ben sorer u'moreh.
Logically a daughter should be able to also be a בן סורר
ומורה, שהכל מצויין אצלה בעבירה. she'kol metzuyin etzla b'aveira. Because if the
concern of a בן סורר ומורה is that if he's going on
this wrong path he's going to lead a life of sin, so
if a woman goes on the wrong path she could turn to
prostitution. So that's a real concern. Now of course that's not the
exact same as the concern of a בן סורר ומורה who will
go and actually be a bandit and kill people, but anyway, אלא
גזירת הכתוב הוא, ela gezeras hakasuv hu, בן ולא בת. ben v'lo
bas. Even if there is more reason, it's the פסוק pasuk is
clear:
only a son, not a daughter. Okay, we will end here.